Guide to the James H. Mills papers 1862-1904
Montana Historical Society
James H. Mills Papers
1862-1904
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 70
Mills, James H. (James Hamilton), 1837-1904
.6 linear feet of shelf space
James Hamilton Mills (1837-1904) edited the Virginia City Montana Post; founded the Deer Lodge New Northwest; and served as Montana Territorial Secretary and State Commissioner of Agriculture, Labor, and Industry. Collection contains: a reminiscence; twenty diaries (1862-1904); and miscellaneous materials concerning Mills' service in the Civil War with the Pennsylvania Infantry, his trip to Montana, politics, and life in Helena, Virginia City, and Deer Lodge.
James Hamilton Mills was born in New Lisbon, Ohio, on December 21, 1837. In April 1861, at the age of 23, Mills enlisted in Company G of the Eleventh Pennsylvania Reserves (Fortieth Pennsylvania Infantry). Through the course of some 27 engagements, Mills was promoted from private to brevet lieutenant colonel before he was mustered out of service in June 1864. On May 24, 1866, Mills traveled from Omaha, Nebraska, to Helena, Montana, arriving on August 12. He initially joined in a company attempting to open a hydraulic claim at Emigrant Gulch, but the effort had to be abandoned because of a lack of provisions. Following this venture, Mills moved to Virginia City, where he was offered the position of editor of The Montana Post. He remained with the Post in Virginia City and Helena until the paper failed in July 1869. At that time, he moved to Deer Lodge and opened the offices of The New Northwest, a newspaper he published and edited until November 1891. James Mills was a lifelong Republican and many times filled important appointed positions. In 1884, he was appointed secretary of the territory by President Hayes. Five years later, after declining nomination to attend the state constitutional convention, Mills accepted the duties of collector of internal revenue for the Montana-Idaho-Utah district, a position he held until February 1893. During the following four years, he served as commissioner of the state Bureau of Agriculture, Labor and Industry. In addition, he was the appointed receiver to the Northern Pacific Railroad in 1895 and to the Helena Consolidated Water Company in 1897. James H. Mills died on September 5, 1904.
The James H. Mills papers contain one reminiscence by Mills about The Montana Post, twenty diaries written between 1862 and 1904, and one account volume from Company G of the 40th Pennsylvania Infantry. The diaries cover Mills' Civil War activities, travel to Montana, newspaper publishing, Republican politics, the elections of 1892 and 1896, the Pullman railroad car strike of 1894, family life, social activities, and territorial government.
Arranged by series. Diaries arranged chronologically.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Mills, James H. (James Hamilton), 1837-1904
Deer Lodge (Mont.)--COMMERCE; Virginia City (Mont.); Virginia City (Mont.)--Periodicals; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Personal narratives
Newspaper publishing--Montana; Political parties--Montana; Strikes and lockouts--Railroads
Montana; Diaries; Publishers and Publishing
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Biographical Materials
  - Reminiscence (re Montana Post editorship), undated (Box-folder 1 / 1)
- Diaries
  - Diaries (3), 1862, 1863, 1865-1866 (Box-folder 1 / 2-3)
  - Diary: "Across the Plains" (includes pencil sketches), 1866-1867 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Diaries (8), 1889-1896 (Box-folder 1 / 5-8)
  - Diaries (8), 1897-1904 (Box-folder 2 / 1-4)
- Outgoing Correspondence
  - Letters of application (drafts), 1895-1896, undated (Box-folder 2 / 5)
- Financial Records
  - Ledger of G Company, Union Army [Civil War], 1862-1863 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
- Miscellany
  - Miscellaneous, 1892-1894 (Box-folder 2 / 7)